<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
               "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <info>
    <title>Flat Tokenizer</title>

    <author>
      <personname><firstname>Gaël</firstname><surname>de
      Chalendar</surname></personname>

      <affiliation>
        <orgname>CEA LIST / LASTI</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <pubdate>07/04/2010</pubdate>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Rationale</title>

    <para>The original tokenizer written by Nautitia was performant concerning
    its tokenization speed, but the automaton on which it was based was too
    complex and described in a too verbose XML format. The automaton
    used subautomatons silently executed when entering some states. These
    subautomatons returning a status possibly used by the transitions of the
    states to chose to fire or not. This was already complex. Furthermore, the
    various transitions were able to advance on the text or not depending on
    the associated actions. Finally, the XML file describing the automaton was
    terribly verbose: for example in French, more than 900 lines for the
    automaton itself, a single transition being described by up to 20 lines
    and more than 1400 lines to describe 211 characters and 39 char
    classes.</para>

    <para>So, each time we had to correct a tokenization error, it took at
    least half a day to understand again the format, to dig into the automaton
    and to make the changes to work. So, I decided to partly rewrite the
    tokenizer to ease the maintenance of the existing automatons and make
    easier the creation of a new automaton for a new language.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Principles</title>

    <para>Two main principles directed the rewrite:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>use a simple description format, easy to read for the human and
        easy to parse for the machine. The resulting French data uses 256
        lines for the automaton and 251 for the chars chart;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>use an automaton simple to understand with a regular and
        systematic behavior: the new automaton systematicaly advance by one
        char (code point) on a successful transition and applies one and only
        one action at a standardized point.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Both file formats are parsed using the Boost.Spirit library which
    allows to define BNF like grammars directly in C++ and to attach code to
    each part of the grammar. This allows to write grammars and exploit them
    very efficiently in our C++ code. This allows also to write little
    validation tools to check the validity of the parsed files. Current tools
    for chars chart and automaton check just verify the basic syntax but it
    will be quite easy to add more semantic check, for example to ensure that
    a state name used is effectively used.</para>

    <para>Both file formats described below support the use of comments
    defined by a '#' and up to the end of the line.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Chars chart</title>

    <para>The chars char lists the characters known by the automaton grouped
    in a hierachy of classes.</para>

    <para>The grammar is ('%' in Spirit means, list of the left part separated
    the right part) in BNF:</para>

    <programlisting>start :: classes chars
classes :: "classes" '{' (classdef % ';')? '}'
chars :: "chars" '{' (chardef % ';')? '}'
identifier :: (alnum | '_')+
classdef :: identifier  ('&lt;' identifier)? ':' (char_ - (';'|eol))+
chardef :: hex ',' (char_ - ',')+ ',' identifier (',' &gt;&gt; modifier % ',')?
modifier :: modifiersymbol hex;</programlisting>

    <para>So, a chars chart is written as</para>

    <programlisting>classes {
# class definitions
}
chars {
# char definitions
}</programlisting>

    <para>The spaces class is called <computeroutput>c_b</computeroutput> and
    it is a kind of delimitor. This is written as</para>

    <programlisting>c_b &lt; c_del : Blank delimitor ;</programlisting>

    <para>where <computeroutput>c_del</computeroutput> is an already defined
    class name. An example of a space character is the tabulation, defined
    as</para>

    <programlisting>0009, CHARACTER TABULATION, c_b ;</programlisting>

    <para>where <computeroutput>0009</computeroutput> is the Unicode code of
    this characted and <computeroutput>c_b</computeroutput> is its class. But
    a character can also be associated to some varaiations of itself,
    introducted by a <computeroutput>modifiersymbol</computeroutput> which is
    an element in the set {'<computeroutput>m</computeroutput>',
    '<computeroutput>M</computeroutput>',
    '<computeroutput>u</computeroutput>'}. For example, 'à' is defined
    as</para>

    <programlisting>00E0, LATIN SMALL LETTER A WITH GRAVE, c_a, M00C0, u0061 ;</programlisting>

    <para><computeroutput>M00C0</computeroutput> means that its majuscule
    version is the character with the code 00C0 ('À') and
    <computeroutput>u0061</computeroutput> (u for unmark) means that its
    unmarked (a generalization of non-accentuated) counterpart is the
    character with the code 0061 ('a'). The last modifier, unused in this
    example is 'm' for the minuscule version of majuscule characters.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Tokenizer automaton</title>

    <para>The automaton is defined by a set of states, each one defined by a
    set of transitions. When arriving on a state, each transition of the state
    is tried in order. The first matching transition is used. So the automaton
    is deterministic. For each transition, The current character in the text
    is checked against the <emphasis>event</emphasis> (a char class) of the
    rule. If it matches, the (optional) conditions, again char classes, on
    previous or next characters are checked. If they matches also, the action
    of the rule is performed. This action can be</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>'/' : forget the currently stored chars</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>'=' : created a token with the currently stored chars and the
        current tokenization statuses</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>'&gt;' : do nothing</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Then, AFTER the action, the (matched with the rule event) current
    char is added to the currently stored chars and the automaton moves to the
    target state of the transition, eventually setting the tokenization status
    of the automaton.</para>

    <para>This behavior is defined by a grammar that can be described in
    BNF-like as:</para>

    <programlisting>start :: state*
state :: '(' identifier ')' '{' transition* '}'
transition :: '-' precondition* event postcondition* transitionsymbol identifier ('(' identifier % ',' ')')?
identifier :: (alnum | '_')+
precondition :: '[' (identifier % '|') ']'
event :: identifier % '|'
postcondition :: identifier % '|'</programlisting>

    <para>The events, pre and postconditions identifiers can be a single char
    class name of a disjonction of such classes that express that any of the
    element will match. The pre and post conditions are classes that must
    appear before or after the current class. The transition symbol is one of
    the symbols listed above and the comma separated identifiers after the
    target state identifier are tokenization status defined in the C++ code.
    These will be defined in the format in a future version.</para>

    <para>Automaton have states for the different kinds of tokens (all
    minuscule, for example) and three special states:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>START : the start state of the automaton which is the state in
        which is the automaton at the beginning;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>IGNORE : which is reached when reading a blank (spaces,
        tabulations, etc.) and which will systematically ignore its current
        char;</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>DELIMITER : which is reached when reading a separator like dot,
        comma, etc. and which will systematically create a token when reading
        its current char.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Development state</title>

    <para>The flat tokenizer is up-to-work. Automatons and lima-lp-*.xml files
    have been converted for all languages but validated (on blocking tva
    tests) only for eng and fre.</para>
  </section>
</article>
